A Finding Aid to the Alexander Archipenko Papers, 1904-1986, bulk 1930-1964, in the Archives of American Art AAA.archalex
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1922-1968; Series 2; 4.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-5
  - Freie Kunstlergemeinschaft, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - G Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Galerie Alex Vomel, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Galerie Anderson-Mayer, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Galerie Charles Lienhard, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Galerie Claude Bernard, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Galerie Europe, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Galerie Gerald Cramer, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Galerie Gurlitt/Galerie Wolfgang Gurlitt, 1953-1963 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Galerie Im Erker, 1962-1965 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Galerie Kriegel, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Galerie Manfred Strake, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Galerie Moderne, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Galerie Stangl, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 33-35)
  - Galerie Wilhelm Grosshennig, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
  - Galleria D'Arte del Grattacielo, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Galleria Nazionale D'Arte Moderna, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Galleria San Fedele, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Galleria Schneider, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Gaulois, Helen, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - George Walter Vincent Smith Art Museum, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Georgette Passedoit Galleries, 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Gertz, Ulrich, 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Golden Gate International Exposition, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Gray, Frances, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Guggenheim Museum, 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - H Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - H.G. Ollendorff Inc., 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Hackley Art Gallery, 1949-1950 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Handler, Milton, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Hanover Gallery, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Harvard University, 1937-1953 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Hessischen Landesmuseums, 1951-1962 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - I Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Instituto Guatemalteco-Americano, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - J Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - James Vigeveno Galleries, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - John Herron Art Institute, 1938-1956 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Josef Schmutz Bollingen, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Josefowitz, David, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - K Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Kansas City Art Institute, 1939-1949 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Karshan, Donald H., 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Katherine Kuh Gallery, 1937-1942 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Katz, Benjamin, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Keck, George Fred, 1949-1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Kestner-Gesellschaft, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Klingler, Marianne Migault, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Kunst Kabinett Klihm, 1955-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Kunstgewerbemuseum Zurich, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Kunstgiesserei August Bischoff, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Kunsthalle Bern, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Kunsthaus Zurich, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - L Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Landeshauptstadt Dusseldorf, 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Lauren Rogers Library and Museum of Art, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Leonard, Mary, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Library of Congress, 1937-1961 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - London County Council, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Los Angeles County Museum, 1944-1956 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - M Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Malisky, Omer, 1936-1938 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Margot, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Marlborough Fine Art Ltd., 1959 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Matthiesen Gallery, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Mellquist, Jerome, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Miami University, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Michigan State College, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Miller, Donna, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Milwaukee Art Institute, 1951-1956 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Moderna Museet, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, 1949-1963 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Musee National D'Art Moderne, 1952-1958 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Museu de Arte Moderna, 1952-1956 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Museum Boymans, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Museum of Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1949-1953 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Museum of Fine Arts of Houston, 1947-1962 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1935-1962 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Museum Nationale Ucrainorum Leopoliense, 1934-1936 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Museum Tel-Aviv, 1947-1961 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - N Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Nair, Eva, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - New York Graphic Society, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Newark Museum, 1939-1962 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Niedersachsische Landesgalerie Hannover, 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Norfolk Museum of Arts and Sciences, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - North Carolina State College, 1954-1959 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - O Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Oland, Edith, 1947-1956 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Orbit Film Corporation Ltd., 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - P Miscellaneous, 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Pasadena Art Museum, 1954-1964 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Perls Galleries, 1958-1964 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Perrine, A.J., 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Philadelphia Art Alliance, 1939-1953 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1939-1956 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Philbrook Art Center, 1949-1962 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Piper, Raymond, 1958-1962 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Princeton University, 1942-1953 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Pritzker, A.N., 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Providence Art Club, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Q-R Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1938-1950 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Riunione Adriatica di Sicurta, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Rose, Billy, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Rosen, Saul, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Rost, Arno, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Rotunda Gallery, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - S Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Saarlandmuseum, 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 72-73)
  - Saltzman, Joan R., 1964 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1939-1951 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - San Jose State College, 1955-1956 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1948-1956 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Santini Brothers, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Schmitz-Hammann, Gabrielle, 1959-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Schmitz-Hillebrecht, Ernst, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Schwarz, Galleria e libreria d'arte, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sculpture in Replica, 1948-1953 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Seattle Art Museum, 1936-1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Semcesen, William, 1954-1960 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Servizi Ritagli Stampa, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Severini, Gino, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Sichel, Pierre, 1962-1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Societe Internationale D'Art, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Soletti, Luciano, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Springfield Museum of Art, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Stadt Duisburg, 1957-1964 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Stadthaus Fuer das Middelheim, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Stadtische Galerie und Lenbachgalerie, 1957-1959 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Stadtische Kunsthalle Manheim, 1955-1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Stadtische Kunsthalle, Recklinghausen, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Stadtisches Karl-Ernst-Osthaus-Museum, 1958-1964 (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
  - Stadtisches Museum Wiesbaden, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - State Teachers College, Pennsylvania, 1952-1956 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - State University of Iowa, 1939-1956 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Stendahl Galleries, 1946-1962 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Svoboda, 1935-1953 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Syracuse Museum of Fine Arts, 1938-1957 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Syracuse University, 1939-1967 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - T Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Tate Gallery, 1958-1963 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - U Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Ukrainian Academy of Art and Science, 1952-1964 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Ukrainian Canadian Committee, 1959-1962 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Ukrainian Institute of America, 1956-1960 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Ukrainian National Association, 1955-1962 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Ullman, Harold, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - United States Information Agency, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - University of British Columbia, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - University of California, 1938-1956 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - University of Chicago, 1950-1952 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - University of Cincinnati, 1938-1954 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - University of Delaware, 1946-1954 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - University of Denver, 1956-1958 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - University of Nebraska, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - University of New Hampshire, 1939-1953 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - University of Oklahoma, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - University of Omaha, 1939-1961 (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
  - University of Oregon, 1951-1955 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - University of Pennsylvania, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - University of Washington, 1953-1963 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - University of Wichita, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - V Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Verdier, Jean, 1952-1964 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Verlag Kiepenheuer and Witsch, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Verlag Ullstein, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - vom Rath, Hanna Becker, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - W Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1964 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Walden, Nell, 1958-1963 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Wallraf-Richartz-Museum, 1958-1963 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Washington University, 1938-1963 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Western Illinois State Teachers College, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Wheelwright, Robert, 1944-1955 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Whitney Museum of Art, 1938-1958 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Wiese, Erich, 1946-1962 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - William A. Farnesworth Library and Art Museum, 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - William Rockhill Nelson Gallery of Art, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Winnipeg Art Gallery Association, 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Witte Memorial Museum, 1947-1949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Y Miscellaneous, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Yale University, 1946-1956 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Z Miscellaneous, 1939-1946 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Zarembsky, Theodore, 1934-1935 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Art Supplies, 1929-1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Letters in German, 1956-1964 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Letters in Russian, 1922-1963 (Box 5, Folder 16-18)
  - Real Estate and Legal Advice, 1925-1964 (Box 5, Folder 19-21)
  - Student Inquiries, Art School, 1936-1958 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Student Inquiries, G.I. Bill, 1944-1950 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Ukrainian Community, 1936-1962 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Unknown and Illegible, circa 1938-1964 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Condolence Letters, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Subject Files, 1940-1958; Series 3; 6 Folders Box 5
  Correspondence concerning many of these subjects may also be found in Series 2: Correspondence. Fraudulent sculpture records include photos and documents concerning a purported Archipenko work, Wieblicher Akt. Gas stove records include diagrams of Archipenko's studio and printed matter about various heating systems. Invention records relate to Archipenko's invention of a stove capable of using five different fuels.
  - Fraudulent Sculpture, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Gas Stoves, circa 1935-1964 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Invention, 1940-1944 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Museum of Modern Art "?That is Why I Request to Remove My Art from the Museum of Modern Art by Alexander Archipenko", 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Myshuha Memorial, 1956-1958 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Shevchenko Monument, 1953-1957 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Writings, 1923-1971; Series 4; 3.1 Linear feet Boxes 5-8
  Archipenko wrote and lectured extensively about his philosophy of art, art in nature, and theories concerning creativity and the universe. He published several articles, but only one of the manuscripts intended as a book was actually published, Archipenko: Fifty Creative Years, 1908-1958 (Tekhne Publications, Inc., 1960). Manuscripts, drafts, notes and supporting materials for Fifty Creative Years survive, along with similar documentation of unpublished writings. Also included are notes, outlines, and some transcripts and audio/visual recordings of lectures and talks. Recordings are on 1 sound cassette, 2 sound tape reels (1/4 in.), and 1 film reel. General notes are extensive and cover a variety of subjects; included with these are names, addresses, and phone numbers for friends, acquaintances, and professional associates in books, a card file, and loose scraps of paper. Writings by other authors consist of short manuscripts about Archipenko.
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries.
  4.1: By Archipenko, 1923-1971
  4.2: By Others, 1953-1957
  Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
  - By Archipenko, 1923-1971; 4.1
    - Articles and Short Writings (Box 5)
      - "Creative Art", circa 1925-1960 (Box 5, Folder 33)
      - "Gravediggers", circa 1925-1960 (Box 5, Folder 34)
      - "Ma", circa 1925-1960 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - "Manifesto" (with Italian and German translations), 1959 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - "Open Letter to the Art Critic, Mr. Zervos", 1939 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - "Polychrome Sculpture", circa 1925-1960 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - "Space, Concave, Light, and Transparency," for Art and Architecture, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - "Universe and Creativity", circa 1925-1960 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Untitled (3 manuscripts), circa 1925-1960 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Archipenko: Fifty Creative Years, 1908-1958 (Box 6)
      - Agreements, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Book Production Correspondence, Estimates Invoices, 1952-1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Distribution Correspondence, Lists, and Expenses, 1960-1972 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Orders and Related Correspondence, Individuals A-Z, 1960-1964 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Orders and Related Correspondence, Institutions and Booksellers, 1960-1972 (Box 6, Folder 5-16)
      - Page Proofs of Illustrations, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder 17)
      - Publication Permissions, A-Z, 1956-1958 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Publicity, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Sales Records, 1960-1961 (Box 6, Folder 20-23)
        Includes 1 bound volume.
      - Tekhne Publications, Inc., Correspondence and Legal Documents, 1957-1965 (Box 6, Folder 24)
      - Draft with Cover Design, circa 1958 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Lists of Archipenko's work, 1949-1963 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Lists of Collectors, circa 1940-1960 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Lists of Exhibitions, circa 1940-1960 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Lists of Exhibitions and Works on Commission, 1937, 1960 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous Notes, circa 1940-1960 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Creativeness, Manuscripts, Drafts, and Notes, circa 1930-1960 (Box 7, Folder 6-10)
    - The Philosophy of Art, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 11-13)
    - Untitled Book about "Creativeness as a Cosmical ( sic) Phenomenon," Manuscript, circa 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Untitled Book about "Creativeness as a Cosmical ( sic) Phenomenon," Research Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Lectures and Talks (Box 7)
      - "Creativity," Lecture Outline, circa 1930-1960 (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - "Creativity and Education," University of Washington, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - "My Credo," Voice of America Broadcast, (with sample copies of broadcasts by others), 1952 (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - "Theme of Archipenko's Lecture in the Saloon of Exhibition of Fundacion Mendoza", circa 1930-1960 (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - Untitled Lecture, Winnipeg, Canada, 1962; 1 sound tape reels Includes transcript. (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - Untitled Lecture, circa 1930-1960 (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - Lecture, "Archipenko: Materials and Color" by Katherine Michaelsen at National Gallery of Art, 1986; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - Conversation among Alexander Archipenko, Dr. Wozniak, Frances Archipenko, and one or more unidentified people, circa 1960-1964; 1 sound tape reels Includes transcript. (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Interview with Archipenko, circa 1940-1964; 1 Film reels (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Notes (Box 7)
      - Address Books, circa 1930-1960 (Box 7, Folder 25-28)
        13 volumes in 4 folders.
      - Address Lists/Mailing Lists, circa 1930-1960 (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Miscellaneous Names and Addresses, circa 1930-1960 (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - Address Card File, A-Z, circa 1930-1960; (3x5 file box) (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
      - Concepts of the Universe, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 5)
        With drawing, photographs, and printed matter.
      - "Dreams ex. For my Book", circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Ceramics, 1938-1950 (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Electroplating, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Enamelling, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Fresco, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Glazes, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Metal Casting, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Metals Coloration, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Miscellaneous, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Pewter, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - Formulae, Instructions, and Supplies - Photography, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - Miscellaneous Notes, 1949-1959 (Box 8, Folder 18-19)
      - Notebook (in Ukrainian), 1923-1927 (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - Notebook (in German and English), circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 21)
        Includes translation of "Archipenko or the Re-examination of a Legend" by Robert D'Hoogle from Frankfurter Allgemeine.
      - "Planetes ( sic) Description and Cells and Description. Chromosomes", circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 22)
        With drawing and photographs.
      - Skeleton and Musculature, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 23)
      - "Source of Art in Nature", circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 24)
        With photographs.
  - By Others, 1953-1957; 4.2
    - Articles about Archipenko by Goll, Hordynsky, Kovaliv, L.M., and Schoffler, 1953-1957 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - "Archipenko Album" by Ivan Goll, circa 1940-1960 (Box 8, Folder 26)
- Teaching, 1921-1952; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet Box 9
  With the exception of one photograph taken in Berlin, 1921, records documenting Archipenko's schools and teaching career are confined to his years in the United States. They focus mainly on his New York City school and the Woodstock summer school, with only a few items representing Chicago.
  The scrapbook contains advertisements and circulars for the Archipenko School of Art, including summer and evening schools, 1932-1946. There are also clippings and other printed matter, including exhibition announcements and catalogs about the Archipenko Art School (1928-1946), Arko Studio (1929), and former students (1931-1941), and a typescript of "How I Teach," a statement by Archipenko. Photographs of students are a group portrait of a class at his school in Berlin, 1921, students in a ceramic workshop, sculpture studios, bronze casting plaster casting, and summer classes, 1923 and 1930. Other photographs are of a pottery kiln, 1930, and Woodstock studio and school buildings, 1930s-1946, including construction views.
  Files regarding Archipenko's teaching activities at schools other than his own include course descriptions, student rosters, grades, and printed matter. There are also 3 video recordings of Archipenko with students; these recordings are on film reels (3.5 in. and 3 in.).
  A small amount of material relating to the Archipenko School and his teaching activities elsewhere is scattered throughout his papers. Series 2: Correspondence includes requests from prospective students for school circulars and other information, correspondence with the various institutions where he was a guest instructor, and correspondence about school advertising. A variety of school related printed matter, as well as clippings about Archipenko's students and their work, and photographs of student exhibitions and student work are included in Series 7: Scrapbooks. Series 11: Photographs contains views of students, classes, and the facilities at Woodstock.
  5.1: Archipenko School, 1921-1952
  5.2: Other Schools, 1946-1956
  - Archipenko School, 1921-1952; 5.1
    - Cash Book, 1931-1934 (Box 8, Folder 27)
      Bound volume; contains names of students.
    - "Concerning the Guild School of Art," a Statement of Archipenko's Philosophy of Teaching, circa 1936 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Printed Matter, 1933-1952 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Scrapbook, "Archipenko Art School, Formerly Ecole D'Art, New York, founded 1923", 1921-1946 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Student Roster, Chicago, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Other Schools, 1946-1956; 5.2
    - Carmel Art Institute, California, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Institute of Design, Chicago, 1946-1947 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - University of British Columbia, Vancouver, Canada, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - University of Delaware, Newark, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - University of Kansas City, Missouri, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - University of Oregon, Eugene, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - University of Washington, Seattle, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - University of Washington, Archipenko with Painting and Sculpture Students, circa 1935-1936; 1 Film reels (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified Institutions, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Institution, Archipenko with students and female model, circa 1940; 1 Film reels (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified Institution, Archipenko with sculpture students, circa 1940-1960; 1 Film reels (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Financial Records, 1923-1971; Series 6; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 9-10
  Financial records include routine banking and billing records, in addition records related to sales and royalties of Archipenko's artwork.
  6.1: Banking Records, 1923-1965
  6.2: Paid Bills, 1935-1971
  6.3: Miscellaneous Financial Records, 1929-1970
  - Banking Records, 1923-1965; 6.1
    - Chemical Bank New York Trust Company, Account of Frances Archipenko, 1963-1964 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Corn Exchange Bank Trust Company/Chemical Corn Exchange Bank, 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 15-16)
    - First National City Bank, 1960-1963 (Box 9, Folder 17-19)
    - First National City Bank, Account of Estate of Alexander Archipenko, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - First National City Bank, Account of Tekhne Publications, Inc., 1960-1964 (Box 9, Folder 21-22)
    - National Bank of Orange and Ulster Counties, 1958-1963 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - New York Trust Company, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Norddeutsche Bank/Deutsche Bank, 1954-1963 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Swiss Bank Corporation/Schweizerischer Bankverein, 1955-1962 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Zivnostenska Banka v Praze, 1923 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Paid Bills, 1935-1971; 6.2
    - Art Supplies, Equipment, and Services, 1945-1971 (Box 10, Folder 1-4)
    - Home Improvements and Upkeep-Bedford St., 1961-1963 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Home Improvements and Upkeep-Woodstock, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Insurance, Automobile, 1958-1964 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Insurance, Homeowners, 1958-1963 (Box 10, Folder 8)